Good morning, Canvas Church. Thank you guys so much for inviting me to be here with you
guys today. My name is Corinne Davidson. And for those of you who do not know me, I just
want to share a little bit of my background, my experience in ministry. So I actually started
about four or five years ago serving as the youth pastor at a fresh church. And then when
COVID hit, transitioned into a season of co-pastoring. And then from there, I found out that I was
having our fifth baby. So I have five children at home, ages ranging from 13, 11, 9, 3, and
soon to be nine months. So God has filled my cliver up. As you can see, I'm very busy, have lots to do.
But God had called us at the end of 21 back to our home church that initially planted a
fresh church. And so now me and my husband and our children were back at Winchester Church of
God. And we're serving the youth ministries there under the leadership of the Cutshaws and
the Islas. So we're into Upward Sports and the Reach Student Ministries and WinKids. And we just really
love reaching out to children and the families in this community. But I'm really, really honored that you
guys have invited me here. You guys are so welcoming. You guys are an amazing group of people. As soon as we
walked out of the car, like into these doors, we just felt like home. So thank you guys so much for being so
inviting. But I am married to Ryan Davidson. Again, we have five kids. And I'm just going to ask God to
bless today's message. And we'll jump in and we'll dive in with the word today. Dear Heavenly Father, we are so
grateful for this opportunity to gather in your presence in your house of worship today. We just
ask God that you would just be with every person in this room. You knew what it took to get us out of
bed this morning to walk us through these doors. You know the heavy burdens and the weights
and the fears and the anxieties and the stresses that we carry with us throughout the week. And God,
we just are so thankful that we're able to find refuge in this house today, in this space today.
That we can lay down those worries and that we can just focus on you, Jesus. That in your presence,
you are with us and you are always, always enough. We just ask you to meet us right where we are today.
I just pray, God, that you would use me to be your vessel, to do whatever it is that you want to do
to reach the hearts of your children sitting in this room. We love you, Father, so much. And we're here
for whatever it is that you want to do in our lives today. We praise your holy name. In Jesus' name we
pray. Amen and amen. All right. So like we had announced earlier, I am going to be going over the fruit of
self-control. So how many of you guys brought your Bibles this morning?
Look, you brought your phones. That's good. So I'm going to encourage you guys, if you have your
phones, follow along. I have a lot of Scriptures to throw out with you. My motto is you don't get in
the car without your keys. You don't go to the store without your wallet. I don't go to church
without my Bible. So keep your Bible on you. And I encourage you guys to take notes today.
I'm really excited for what the Lord has in store. So if you are taking notes, which I encourage you
to do so, today's sermon title is called Less is More, the fruit of self-control. Less is more.
How many of you guys get in trouble with overspending or overindulging? Whether it's watching too much TV,
whether it's spending too much money on Amazon, whether it's eating too much ice cream or queso at
your favorite Mexican restaurant when you know that you are lactose, right? That's right. Or speeding
tickets, right? So we really want to get in this concept that less is more, but in our Christian
faith walk, I just want us as believers, as children of God, as brothers and sisters, we have to get past
that superficial Christianity, getting past the part where we think that we have to perform
and we lose our passions and we lose sight of what really matters, who really matters. Because
everything that we do in our Christian walk, whether we are serving in full-time ministry, whether we are
working out in the community, working in the schools, in our marriages, at home with our children,
every single thing that we do should be for the glory of Jesus Christ, right? So that's what we're going
to go after today. So first Scripture that I have for you guys is in 2nd Timothy, chapter 1, verse 7.
And I think it's on the screen, but if not, I'll read it out with you. You can have some time to get
there. 2nd Timothy, chapter 1, verse 7. And Scripture tells us, for God has not given us a spirit of fear
or timidity, but of power, love, and self-discipline. Power, love, and self-discipline. That self-discipline
is our self-control. And the first thing that I'm going to encourage you guys to understand about power,
when we have authority and we have power, that power is not controlling the circumstances around you
or the people around you. That's not what power is. Real power is the ability to control yourself in
spite of others or the current circumstances that you may be facing right here, right now.
A lot of us, we fall into this trap of thinking that if we could just control our husbands or if we can
just control our wives or if we can just control our children or control the people in our workspaces,
if we can just control politics or social media, if we can just get the control on these things that are
really outside of our control, we leave the lie that then, then it'll be okay. Then I will be happy.
And that's not what the Bible teaches us. Trying to control anything outside of you is the very first
sign that you are actually out of control. So let's go through some very deep questions. We're going to
self-evaluate because when we self-evaluate, we become self-aware. So here's some questions that
we can ask ourselves this morning. What can I actually control? What am I actually in control of?
Well, you can control your attitude. You can control your attitude when you had a bad day at work and
you're coming home to your family. They don't need the repercussions of your bad attitude because you got
upset with somebody at work, right? You can control your attitude. You can control your perspective.
You were really looking forward to this promise, this outcome, and everything was there. You put in
for it and you were told that you were going to receive this really awesome gift and you're so
excited. This promotion was going to be all yours. And then suddenly something changed and now you've been
let down, you've been rejected and you feel like, you know, this was it. Like now all my dreams and all
my goals and everything is over. If we control our perspective and realize that it's not over,
the dream's not over, the promise is not over. God just has bigger and better things in store for
you. He died for it. He rose for it and he already knows what your future holds. So you can control your
perspective and just believe God that the best is yet to come. You can control your words and how you
communicate. Just because you can say something doesn't mean that you should, but how you say it
really matters. It's the tone of your voice, how you say things. You guys learned about gentleness
already. We know to be gentle and kind, right? You can control your thoughts. The Bible tells us to take
captive our thoughts, to be mindful of the things that you're allowing and inviting into your life to
manipulate your mind. TV shows, the music that you listen to, what kind of lyrics are running through
your brain all day, social media, outside opinions. We allow circles and people and gossip, books, culture.
We allow all these things to shape our mind when really and authentically we should be trusting Jesus
in the word of God because as Christians, as believers, that's what we're called to do. Believe
the word of God, follow the word of God, align ourselves with what he says. You can control your
ability to be present and you can control your ability to say no. Just because you can say yes
doesn't mean that you should. Sometimes we bite off more than we can chew and then we invite a lot of
stress and chaos into our lives. We run late and we bite off more than we can chew and we don't serve
others well when we do that. We don't give our best when we do that. We have the power and the control
to set boundaries. We have the control to be good listeners. When somebody trusts you with their heart
and you're sitting with your spouse at the dinner table or for a date for the first time, instead of
getting out your phone, you can actually listen and take time to hear what the people in front of you
are saying. See them, listen to them, be approachable because Jesus was always approachable. He set that
ultimate example of allowing people to come to us and listening to them and seeing them for who they
really are in the season they're in right now. You can control your effort, giving the best of
yourselves, your conscience decision to keep on learning and to keep on growing. We're people. We're human.
We fail. We make mistakes. We get grumpy. We get moody. We get worn out. We get stressed and so we snap and
just because we fail, just because we make a mistake doesn't mean that we should stop there. We have to be
really intentional about making amends and continuing to work on our personal growth.
You can control your priorities, your faith, how much time do you spend with God each day, your family,
your marriage, your health, your community, your dreams, your goals, your energy, your time. All of
that is in your control. It is in your control to maintain your environment and your space, where
you're working, where you're thriving. And lastly, you have the ability to control your breath. Some of us
just need to stop where we are and remember who God is and just take that big, deep breath. Can
everybody do that with me this morning? Just do you guys know that in Hebrew literature, there was never
a name for God. His name is so sacred and so holy that Yahweh, we say Yahweh, that's the name, Hebrew name for
God. But really, it was just a breath. It was just stopping to breathe. That's what the real sound is.
Y-W-H-W is just a sound. And sometimes we need to remember that that's enough to just call on the name
of God to breathe. And I want to encourage you guys to consider this today. So we talked about all these
things instead of our control. And I just want you to consider your environment. I want you to consider
your school, your work, your home, your marriage. Consider your environment. You're working in an
environment that is crowded, overly crowded, overly messy, too much stuff, too many sticky notes, full of
artificial light. You haven't been out in the sun. You haven't been out in nature for a long time to
see what God's doing. And you're just surrounded by all of the superficial sounds and noises.
And it has been proven scientifically. Studies have shown that all of this noise and chaos and
clutter has a negative effect on one's physical and mental well-being. And so does living in a space
that is stuffed with unnecessary things that bring no value and no joy to your life work the lives of
others. Because as a Christian, it's not just about you. It's about the people around you, too.
Because you always have room to make a difference and impact. So consider this with me this morning.
I think we would all agree in the same room together, brothers and sisters, just having
like table talk right now, that too much stuff, unnecessary stuff, leads to unnecessary stress.
How many of you guys find yourself living that kind of life every week? Just too much stuff is
leading to unnecessary stress in your life. And the things that we allow to pile up and overwhelm us in
our homes will always prevent us from having the home that we truly, fully desire. And it prevents us
from enjoying our life to the fullest. And that's what Jesus came to do. He came to empower us to
live our lives to the absolute fullest. The same concept goes for all the clutter and the baggage that
we allow to pile up in our spiritual homes. Amen. Because the Bible tells us that our bodies,
our physical bodies are a temple for the Holy Spirit. We house the living Spirit of God. How cool is that?
That's amazing. But sometimes we go through seasons and we're like, God, where are you? You're not here
with me. You've neglected me. You forgot about me for me because we don't see him. We don't see the
promise. We don't see what he's doing because we've neglected to clean out our spiritual homes.
We've allowed a lot of junk and cluttered the pile up. Failed marriages. We bark at our children and
now our children won't talk to us. We've lost our teenagers, our communities. We've made mistakes
at work. We've lied. We've got that speeding ticket, that secret addiction that you keep hiding that's
got a secret control over your life. And we've lost our grip on things.
The amount of stress that we experience will always be because of the clutter that we're
not focusing on fixating, getting out of our lives right here, right now. That's why God calls us to
repent. Because if we truly want to see God, walk with God, walk with Jesus, we've got to repent,
turn away from the baggage, turn away from the clutter, and turn our faces back to God so that
we can hear him and see him in our everyday walk. With the lack of self-awareness, it can be easy to
accumulate not only physical junk, loads of debt, marital issues, habits, dysfunctional relationships,
and toxic patterns of guilt and compensation. How often do we do that? We explode at somebody,
or we make a mistake, or we're mean, or we're crude, and we're ugly and nasty, and then we put money out
because we think that a materialistic thing is going to make it better. And we keep putting
materialistic, worldly band-aids on what really, truly needs a spiritual cleansing.
In UCLA's Center on Everyday Lives of Families, they performed a systematic study on the home life and
found that individuals who felt overwhelmed by clutter in their homes tend to be less satisfied in their
marriage, less motivated, and less desiring to spend quality time with their families.
They have a difficult time managing everyday tasks. They feel ineffectual, worthless, ashamed.
They suffer depression. They have increased fatigue where they just desire to stay in bed. They have no
motivation. And they have unhealthy hormonal spikes and stress patterns that not only affect them but the
people around them. Housework and chores become the competitors they can keep for attention and time,
turning our homes into a prison of demands rather than a refuge for rest. And that's where we find
ourselves. And again, 1 Corinthians 6:19 tells us that our bodies are the temples of the house of the
the spirit of the living God. We house the spirit of the living God. But sometimes I think that we forget to
make room for God's divine presence in our lives. It's not that he's not there. We just can't see him
beyond all the stuff that we're holding on to. So I'm going to encourage you guys today to get beyond the
clutter, beyond the pressure, beyond the weight, beyond all the junk and all the garbage that you just seen
that you can't let go of for whatever reason. So we're going to turn together in 1 Samuel chapter 24.
And we're going to look at one of my favorite examples of self-control.
Now a little background while you guys are turning to 1 Samuel 24. We all know about that little shepherd boy
David, right? And this was so cool because when Pastor Ryan invited me to come speak, I was praying
about it. And this was the verse that or the chapter account that God had placed upon my heart. And then
last Sunday, I was sitting in a sermon and the pastor actually mentioned this chapter and it was just
confirmation for me. I was like, "Okay, God, like, I know that you want me to take this and
you want to speak life into these Scriptures to your children's hearts." So we look at this little boy named David,
who's a little shepherd boy who takes care of sheep. And he's walked with God his whole life. He has these
encounters and these experiences with God since he was a child. And this little shepherd boy has been chosen to
become the king of Israel, the next king of Israel. And not only is he going to be the greatest king that Israel
ever has, but through him, through his bloodline, there is going to be a savior, a redeemer that's
going to come and bless every single nation. He's coming back to atone all the nations outside of
Israel. And so we have this little boy named David, and we know that he has protected his sheep with his
bare hands from lions and bears. And he's killed lions and bears with his bare hands. And that doesn't
make sense to us, but this is a true account. This is what the Bible says. And the same boy goes up to
feed his brothers who are serving in Saul's army, who is the current king of Israel. And they're going
up against these savage Philistines. And there's this one Philistine named Goliath, this giant, and he's
mocking God's people. He's mocking God. He's tearing the people of God down. And David goes,
how dare this man speak about the Lord like this? He's like, this is not okay. So the same little boy
David goes and faces this giant, and he takes him down with one sling and one stone. And so that's the
same David that we have now. And Saul, who is still proud of David at the time, has now turned his view of
David. He's grown in envy and jealousy because it's not his bloodline anymore that's going to be
ruling over Israel. And he just, he doesn't like that idea. So now David has been chased down by Saul
and his men, his army, for the last 10 years. And they're running rampant. He's running for his
lives. And he has people who are following him. They're trusting in David. They see him as God's
anointed one. And so they're all in with David. And so they're running for their lives from this man
named Saul, the king Saul, because Saul has turned his back on God and he's kind of lost his anointing.
And so that's kind of where we are right now, just to have a little bit of context. So in chapter 24,
it starts off and it says, after Saul returned from fighting the Philistines, he was told that David
had gone into the wilderness, I mean Gedi. And so Saul chose 3,000, 3,000 alight troops from all of
Israel and they went and searched for David and his men near the rocks of the wild goats.
At the place where the road passes, some sheepfold, Saul went into a cave to relieve himself to take a
nap. He's tired. He's, he's fighting these hasty Philistines. So he's going to go take a rest. But as it
happened, David and his men were hiding further back in that same cave, in that very cave. And now David's
men are all whispering, all the noise starts coming in, David, Saul, this is your opportunity.
David's men are whispering to him today, the Lord is telling you, I will certainly put your enemy into
your power to deal with as you wish. And so David, he's listening to all the opinions of his men and
he's like, surely, like this must be it. God would not put Saul, like of all the caves around the
area, Saul came to this cave that we were hiding in. Like this has got to be the moment. So David
creeps up and he cuts off a piece of the hem of Saul's robe. But then David's conscience kicks in
and it begins to bother him because he had cut Saul's robe. He hadn't even done anything
traumatically wrong. He just cut off a little piece of the robe of this man sleeping in the cave with
him who's been trying to kill him for the last 10 years, hunting him down like a wild animal.
And he says to his men, the Lord forbid that I should do this to my Lord, the King. I shouldn't
attack the Lord's anointed one for the Lord himself has chosen him. And so David restrained himself and
his men and he did not let them kill Saul. Can you imagine? I mean, I'm a female, but can you
imagine being a man in this position where you have this group, this army of men who are following you?
They trust in you. You are responsible for them and their livelihood. And they believe that you're the
next king in life and the enemy is right there and he's sleeping and you're not going to go
take care of it. We're going to have to keep on running for our lives. Why would you ever put
us in this kind of position? Could you imagine the thoughts that are going through his mind,
David's mind at this time, where the men who are trusting him, because maybe they're like,
maybe we're foolish. Maybe we shouldn't be trusting this guy after all. What is David doing?
So after Saul had left the caves and he'd gone on his way, David comes out and he shouts after his
enemy. He calls him, my Lord, the King. Could you imagine doing that? Could you imagine looking your
your foe in the eye and saying, hi, my Lord, my King? What is going on in these Scriptures?
He said, when Saul looked around, David bows low to the ground before him. Not only does he call out to
his enemy, not only is he calling out to Saul, but now he gets down in the dirt and he puts his face in
the dirt and he bows down before this man. He wants to kill him, murder him, shred him and his men to
pieces. This doesn't make sense. But nothing in God's story really makes sense because that's who God
is. He does the unimaginable to wake people up, to show us that there's more to life than the human
mind can comprehend. And so he shouts out to Saul and he says, why do you listen to the people who say
that I'm trying to harm you? This very day, you can see with your own eyes that it isn't true,
for the Lord placed you at my mercy back there in that cave. Some of my men told me to kill you,
but I spared you, for I said, I will never harm the King. He is the Lord's anointed one. Look,
my father, at what I have in my hand, it is a piece of the hem of your robe. I cut it off,
but I did not kill you. This proves to you that I'm not trying to harm you and that I have not
sinned against you, even though you have been hunting me down to kill me. May the Lord judge
between us. I put it in the Lord's hands now. Perhaps the Lord will punish you for what you have
been trying to do to me, but I will never harm you. As that old proverb says, from evil people come
evil deeds. So you can be sure I will never harm you. Who is the King of Israel trying to catch
anyway? Should he spend his time chasing the one who is as worthless as a dead dog or a single flea?
Do you see what David does with his own status right there? He compares himself to a dead dog.
He compares himself to a flea. He's like, you're the King of Israel. Who am I? Why are you chasing
after me in the first place? We have Philistines out here. We have a real enemy to go after,
but you're jealous of me. You're fighting me. And then he says, may the Lord therefore judge
which of us is right and punish the guilty one because God is my advocate and he will rescue me
from your power. I don't know how, I don't know why, but he's telling me not to kill you,
to not take you into my hands, to not take revenge in my own hands. So I'm not going to do it. I'm just
going to trust in the Lord, even when, even if it doesn't make sense.
And Saul's response, when David had finished speaking, Saul calls back, is that really you,
my son David? Because remember, they once had a father-son relationship. David is the best friend
of his son Jonathan. And Saul began to weep. He begins to cry. And he said to David, you are a
better man than I am, for you have repaid me good for evil. Yes, you have been amazingly kind to me
today. For when the Lord put me in a place where you could have killed me, you chose not to do it.
Who else would let his enemy get away when he had him in his power? May the Lord reward you well
for the kindness you have shown to me today. And now I realize that you are surely going to be king
and that the kingdom of Israel will flourish under your rule. Now swear to me by the Lord that when
this does happen, you will not kill my family or destroy my line of descendants. And so David promised
this to Saul with an oath. And then Saul went home. But David and his men went back to their stronghold.
See, David didn't take his enemy under his control. He just simply took his control of himself and his
response to a really hard and a really difficult situation. Despite what people thought he should do,
what culture thought he would do, he simply gave it to God and he trusted God more than anything else.
A lot of times when we read the Bible and we read these Scriptures, we like to find ourselves in these
stories, right? And we like to see ourselves as the hero or sometimes we see ourselves as the victim.
But in this scenario, in this case, Jesus is the David and we are the Saul. It is our sins that have been
hunting down him and we are in denial about it. We don't realize how much our sins separate us from
God and we don't like the truth and we don't like the word and we don't like the fruit that it produces.
And we think we're chasing after fruit, but what we're really chasing after is a God that tells us what
we want to hear. And so we go to cut down the fruit that he's offering to us, the love, the joy, the peace,
the patience, the kindness, the goodness, the faithfulness, the gentleness, and the self-control.
And see, Jesus put himself in that humble position when he got done in the garden and he prayed for us.
He wasn't just praying for his disciples, he was praying for us. Every single person that's in this
room today, he prayed. He wept until his driplets of blood or his sweat was dripping with blood.
That's how much anguish he was in. He was in high levels of stress. But he prayed for you that you
might know him, that you might continue to carry out his will, to build up the church, to bring him glory,
to bring him honor, to simply have a pure relationship with him. He got down in the dirt for us.
And sometimes we need to step back and self-evaluate because I think sometimes we see ourselves as
gods. We climb up on this pedestal and then we expect other people to live up to our standards
when we haven't even been working to live up to Christ. So let me ask you this. What happens when we allow
certain habits and behaviors in our lives to become unruly? It's out of control. It's unruly. It's
overgrown. It's a waste. You've probably heard of the phrase, don't put off tomorrow until tomorrow what
you could get done today, right? We've all heard that little phrase, right? We will never live out our
Christian lives, following Jesus, fulfilling God's will, and pleasing the Father without the fruit of
self-control. It's impossible to feed the flesh and to feed the spirit at the same time.
And this relates so much to me. I am a homeschool mom, so not only do I have five children,
a little bit of a button when it comes to just, I guess, living in pain these days, but I decided to
homeschool all of my children and I have teenagers and pots running around my home and we have two
really energetic puppies. And my husband, when we first moved into our home, our first home,
he did something really special for me. Because I homeschool, we do a lot of hands-on. And he built
me this garden box so that me and the kids could go outside and have a time escape out of the house.
And, you know, our soil is too rocky, so we couldn't really plant a garden in our backyard. But he built
this above-ground box and he took the time to measure it. And it's quite large. And it's where we plant
our fruits and our vegetables. And on the outside edges of this above-ground garden, there's space to where
we can put herbs and marigolds and lavender, things that draw in the pollinators but kind of drive away
the past. And so he put a lot of thought into this. And he's mixing the soil and he takes me and the kids
outside. And he has all these bags that I have no idea what he's doing. But there's soil and there's
fertilizer and there's minerals and nutrients. And he's just hand-mixing all of this dirt. It all looks
the same to me. But he's like, no, this is the right stuff. And he's putting all this time and energy
into this box that I wanted. And he's mixing the dirt and we plant in our seedlings and our little seeds. And
before long, they start to sprout up. And at this time in my life, I was in full-time ministry. And I kept
telling myself every day I would look at my garden and it was getting bigger and bigger and homeschooling and
crunching numbers and answering emails and fixing dinner but then not even being able to eat dinner with my family because I
would run and rush out the door because I would have another meeting or somebody needed counseling. And I was just
always on the go. And I thought the busier I was, the more I was pleasing God. And I kept looking out there at my
little garden. And it just, you know, these tomato plants. And if you didn't know, the real summer fruit is the
tomato. And it's growing up really big. And it's wild and it's unruly. And I keep saying, I got to prune this thing. I got to
cut off these fruitless branches or else my tomatoes aren't going to ripen. They're not going to, they're
going to stay green. They're not going to turn red. And it's going to be a waste. Everything that we did
this summer is going to be wasted. And I said, I'll get to it tomorrow. And then another third meeting
would pop up or somebody else would call and there was more on demand. And I would say, I get to it
tomorrow. I get to it tomorrow. Until finally tomorrow didn't come. And I went outside to my garden
and my tomato plants had completely uprooted out of the box. And they were out of the ground,
out of the soil. They're green and they're withering. And I just looked at it and I was
like so ashamed and so embarrassed. And I was like, what is my husband going to think? Like
this was a really generous gift that he gave to me. And I didn't steward it very well. I was
supposed to come out here with my children every day and teach them how to cultivate this garden
and nurture this garden. And I didn't find the time. I didn't make it a priority.
And when he sees this, what is he going to think? What is he going to say? What is he
going to do? And God blessed me with a really good man because when he came home and you
know how emotional women can be and I'm not going to deny it. I can be pretty emotional at
times. I was so upset and embarrassed and ashamed. And my husband comes out and he just looks
at the mess and he gets down in the dirt with me. And he gets out his pruning shears and
he starts to cut away the dead branches and then he gets out the trellis, the tomato cages
and he replants these tomato plants. Instead of letting them go to waste, it would have been
a lot easier just to throw them into the wheelbarrow and take them to the garbage, to
the dump. But instead he cuts away all the dead pieces, all the waste. And he replants them
and he puts these cages around them, not to retain them or contain them or restrict them,
but to give them the extra support that they've been needing. And then he takes some twine and
heme and ties off some of the branches to help it stay up because it was pretty weak. And
then we kept watering it and taking care of it. And we had a full harvest. We made the best
fresh salsa that summer and tomato sandwiches and marinara. And my husband in that moment reminded
me of Christ and Jesus. And I needed that in my life. I needed that reminder that when I make a
mess, when I get too busy, when I lose my temper, that Christ is always willing to get down in the
dirt with me. He gets down in my dirt, in my mess. And he says, here, let me help you. It's not over.
It's not wasted. You're not trash. You're not garbage. We just need to prune it up. We just need to
clean up just a little bit. And once we get it cleaned up and tidied up and we remove all that
fruitless clutter, all that fruitless branches from your life, then you're able to receive my
living water. And then my fruits will flourish in your life. And then we will be able to be those
Christ-like people to our neighbors, to our family. And my husband reminded me of that. And I think that
we're called. We need people in our lives to do that for us, but we also have to be willing to do that
for other people. Don't be afraid of the pruning in your life.
At some point in our Christian lives, we have to be for hope over hype. We have to be for faith over
fear. And we have to be for truth over tolerance. That's simply what it is. God is coming back. Jesus
is coming back. The Scriptures tell us that he's coming back. He's coming back for a bride, a blameless,
spotless bride. And he's not asking us to be perfect. He's just simply asking us to walk with
him. In John chapter 10, verse 10, it says, the thief comes only to steal, to kill, and to destroy. But I
came so that they might have life and have it abundantly, have it to the fullest. The truth is,
is that Jesus wants you to experience the fullness of God and his promises for you, for your life,
for your family, right here, right now, beyond this life's social norms, what culture says, the pressures,
the fears, the anxieties, the tension. In Luke chapter 9, verse 23, he said to them,
If anyone desires to come after me, let him deny himself and pick up his cross daily. And then follow me. We have work to do in ourselves. In Christ, with the help of the Holy Spirit, we hold the power to respond to things that are sent to destroy our peace. We have power over them. We believe these lies when it comes to self-control. These are lies that we believe.
We tell ourselves. We say, I have this under control. I have my addiction under control. It's just a little bit of pornography. I have it under control. It's just an emotional affair. I'm not physically cheating on my spouse. I have this under control. It's just tender outside of wedlock. It's just a little bit of sin. At least it's not as bad as. And we start comparing it. I could be like them, but I'm not.
And then we tell ourselves this big lie. This is the last time. Just one more time, and then it'll be it. And it'll be done. I won't do it again.
And then we tell ourselves an even bigger lie. I'm not really hurting anyone. If you're not hurting anyone, but you're hurting yourself, you're still missing out on the calling on your life to impact future generations, your children, and their children, and their children, and so on and so forth.
The truth is, in Christ, we have been given the measure of faith that produces the fruit of self-control, giving us power and authority over our thoughts, over our emotions, over our actions, enabling us to become more aware of our surroundings, resisting temptation,
and ultimately saying no to the sin in our lives that's trying us, and keeping us down, and keeping us and preventing us from our true calling and mission to glorify God, to build up his church.
There are plenty of examples, plenty of examples throughout Scripture, of the great consequence for the lack of self-control.
We see it in Eve, Cain, Esau, Jonah, Peter, even David, even the David that we talked about today.
They've all lacked self-control, and they all experienced very harsh consequence because of it.
And it teaches us one really important lesson.
What if, and if you're taking notes, write this question down.
What if you keep putting off for tomorrow, Christ came back for today, right now?
He's coming to get his bride.
Are we ready?
Are our children ready?
Proverbs 16.32 tells us, better to be patient than powerful.
Better to have self-control than to conquer an entire city.
You never have to manipulate God's manifestation in your life.
In 1 Corinthians 9, verse 25, it says,
All athletes are disciplined in their training.
They do it to win a prize that will not fade away, or that will fade away.
They train for a prize that will fade away, but what we're doing as Christians, the mission of Christ,
we're working towards an eternal prize that will never fade away.
It's an unshakable reward.
In 1 Corinthians 10, verse 13, it says,
The temptation in your life, the temptations in your life are no different from what others experience.
And God is faithful.
We have to remember the next time that we drive up to the ABC store,
or we want to smoke that cigarette, or we want to talk to that person that we really shouldn't be talking to,
we have to remember that God is faithful.
And maybe it's our turn to get down and kneel to the ground in the dirt because Christ did it for us
until those temptations go away.
He will not allow the temptation to be more than what you can stand.
And when you are tempted, he will show you a way out so that you can endure and keep on enduring.
In 1 Thessalonians 5, 6,
So then, let us not sleep as others do, but let us stay awake and be sober and alert.
Remember who our real enemy is.
People are not our enemies.
We have a real enemy out there, and he is on the prowl like a hungry lion waiting to devour you in your moments of weakness.
Galatians 4, 13 tells us that we can do everything through Christ who gives us strength.
You set your mind to it, you take captive those thoughts, and you believe Jesus when he says that you can overcome.
It is by his stripes, it is by his wounds that we have been healed.
In Romans 8, 11,
If the spirit of him who raised Jesus from the dead dwells inside of you,
he who raised Christ Jesus from the dead will also give life to your mortal bodies
through the same spirit that dwells and lives inside of you.
God's spirit lives inside of you.
The same spirit that raised Jesus from the dead, you have access to.
Luke 10, 19,
Behold, I have given you authority to tread on serpents and scorpions and over all the power of the enemy,
and nothing will hurt you.
And finally, as we wrap up today's message,
we'll go back to the fruits of the Spirit.
Galatians 5, 19 through 25.
It says,
The acts of the flesh are obvious.
Sexual immorality, impurity and debauchery, idolatry and witchcraft, hatred, discord, jealousy, fits of rage, selfish ambition, dissensions, factions, and envy, drunkenness, orgies, and the like.
And I warn you, as I warn you, as I did before, that those who live like this will not inherit the kingdom of God.
But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, faithfulness, gentleness, and self-control.
But against such things there is no law.
Those who belong to Christ Jesus have crucified the flesh with its passions and desires.
And since we live by the spirit of God, let us keep in step with the spirit.
Let us not become conceited, provoking, and envying each other.
Church, I'm going to ask you today, what in your life are you trying to control outside of you?
Is it your marriage?
Is it your husband?
Is it somebody else's addiction?
Maybe you have convinced yourself that this is just the way it is.
This is just who I am.
I challenge you to take captive those thoughts and align them with what God's word says about you and believe them.
And then evaluate what areas in your life are completely out of control, unruly.
And what areas are you needing to stop giving into your emotions?
Stop being led by your feelings and trust in the word of God and the spirit of God.
Knowing and believing that God is faithful and he will rescue you and he will restore you and he will finish every good thing that he starts.
All you have to do is bring it to him and ask him for that deliverance, for that refuge, for that rest.
And finally, if you have never asked or invited Jesus to come into your heart, into your life, to be your personal Lord and Savior,
I challenge you to consider that today.
Consider a life with Christ, a life fueled by the spirit of God, surrendering all the stress, all the clutter,
all the pressures of this life, and just trusting God with it all, giving all of your control over to him, believing him, and experiencing that full life in abundance.
Will you all stand with me today?
Every head bowed, eyes closed, brothers and sisters, hear me out.
We are living in a world that is unfolding of Christ's return.
Jesus not only died for your sins, but he rose again to promise you the gift of his Holy Spirit that will empower you to live out heaven on earth right here, right now.
In your homes, in your workspaces, in your schools, in your marriages, with your children.
Everywhere you go, you can bring a blessing upon not only yourself, but the people around you.
Christ is coming back one day.
We don't know when, but he will return.
Why not take hold of those promises right here, right now, until that day comes?
Dear Heavenly Father, we are so grateful for your presence in this room.
We are so grateful for your children.
We're so grateful for this opportunity to fellowship, to just take in your word, to chew on it, to savor it.
I pray, God, that you are just removing hearts of stone in this place today.
I pray, God, that you are refueling passions and fire that have burned out.
I just pray, God, that you are restoring marriages and families in this house today.
I pray, God, that you are rekindling people and their relationship and their faith walk with you.
That we do not have to deconstruct our faith, God, but we just need to re-self-evaluate.
That you are God and you are good.
And that, Jesus, you are the only way.
That we don't have to perform for miracles.
That we don't have to perform for joy.
We don't have to live in an artificial, superficial lighting.
We don't have to wear a mask.
We can just simply come together and be ourselves.
And you say that we are an imperfect people who serve a really good, perfect God.
And that he takes our ashes and he brings us back to life and makes all things beautiful.
God, you know the weights that we carry throughout the week, throughout the days.
You know the thoughts that taunt us day in and day out.
And God, I just pray that we have the strength to lay them down at the foot of the cross today.
That we pick up our own crosses.
That we would just lay down anything that does not serve you, that does not please you, or serve your kingdom or your people or our brothers and sisters in Christ.
May we not allow ourselves to be tricked or fooled by the enemy.
May we not partake of things that cause one another to stumble.
May we keep our eyes on you and run this race to the fullest with our best effort and energy, with full passion and full hearts on fire for you, Lord.
So that one day we can look you in the eye and hear, well done, my good and faithful servants.
We love you, Jesus.
And we're so excited for this beautiful thing that you are doing in each of us and in our community.
We love you so much.
In Jesus' name, amen.
Amen.